Guide to the Howard Olson Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Howard Olson Family Papers
1943-2010
RG 238
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.5
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of Howard and Louise Olson and their family. The Olsons were Lutheran missionaries and educators in Tanzania from 1946 to 1988. Howard Olson was instrumental in translating the New Testament into the Rimi language and had a particular interest in African music and hymns.
Olson, Howard S.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Olson family, 2011
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Howard S. Olson was born July 18, 1922 and died July 1, 2010. He received a B.A. from Gustavus Adolphus College, an M.Div. from Augustana Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Hartford Seminary (1965). In 1946 Howard married Louise Anderson, daughter of George and Annette Anderson, who were missionaries serving under the Augustana Lutheran Mission in Tanganyika Territory 1924-1954. Howard and Louise had four children: Howard, Sharon, Timothy, and Linda.
Howard and his wife Louise served as Lutheran missionaries in Tanzania from 1946 to 1988, collaborating in parish work, educational work, and in the study of African music. During the first half of their career Howard worked mainly as a parish pastor, builder, Bible translator, language teacher and administrator. He analyzed and reduced to writing a dialect of the Rimi language and assisted in completing the first draft translation of the New Testament in Rimi.
Howard and Louise both taught at Makumira Seminary, the largest Lutheran seminary in Africa, for twenty-four years. Howard was Director of Music Research and served from time to time as President, Academic Dean, chair of the Biblical Department, chaplain, and editor of The Africa Theological Journal. Louise taught a variety of subjects to the theological students and their wives, was active in the seminary choir, and worked in conjunction with her husband in notating ethnic music.
Howard also taught at Pacific Lutheran Theological Seminary, the Lutheran School of Theology in Chicago, and Wartburg Theological Seminary. He published works in the fields of theology, ethnomusicology and linguistics in English, Kiswahili and Kirimi. Major publications include The Phonology and Morphology of the Rimi Language, Jifunze Kiyunani (textbook for teaching Koine Greek in Swahili), Tumshangilie Mungu (six editions of 150 ethnic hymns in Swahili with translation of some of them in English, German, and French), Lead Us, Lord and Set Free (compilations of African ethnic hymns published by Augsburg Fortress). Hymns by Olson can be found in many Evangelical Lutheran Church in America hymnals. In the 1990s and early 2000s, the Olsons gave presentations and taught at various conferences and lay courses related to Africa and African music.
Scope and Contents
This collection provides valuable documentation of the life and work of Howard and Louise Olson as Lutheran missionaries in Tanzania, including their educational work, research related to African music and languages, and the experience of raising children in a missionary setting. The family correspondence from the 1940s and 1950s provides more detailed information about their work in Tanzania. There is no correspondence from the 1960s and the correspondence beginning with the 1970s is primarily with the Olson's children, focusing more on their lives, but with some mention of the Olsons' activities in Tanzania.
The Writings of Series II primarily relate to Howard Olson's work in the areas of linguistics and African music. Additional documentation regarding African music and hymns is found in Series III. The documentation of Conferences and Lay Courses in Series IV includes the Olsons' teaching curricula related to Africa and African music as well as records from reunions of Lutheran missionaries to East Africa. Series V, Collected Material, includes photocopies of historical documents related to the Lutheran mission in Tanzania and two audiotapes related to African languages. The collection concludes with Series VII, Biographical Documentation.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1945-1988, n.d.
II. Writings, 1955-2004
III. African Music Documentation
IV. Conferences and Lay Courses, 1994-2004, n.d.
V. Collected Material, 1943-1991, n.d.
VI. Biographical Documentation, 2010, n.d.
Hymns, African; Hymns, Swahili; Singida District (Tanzania) -- Languages; Olson, Howard S.; Lutheran Theological College (Makumira, Tanzania)
- Correspondence, 1945-1988, n.d.; Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - HSO to parents incl. re. beginning mission work in Tanzania; working with Louise's parents; learning Swahili; moving to another station; Louise pregnancy and death of child at birth., 1945 Nov - 1949 Apr (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Incl. re. traveling, hunting, famine problem, electricity installed at mission; HSO elected secretary of mission; sewing classes, translation work for hymnal completed, 1949 May - 1950 Jan (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Incl. re. collecting native melodies and words - samples from five tribes; malaria persists, 1950 Feb-Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Incl. re. more hymns translated; Louise's parents return to field; refresher course for 130 teachers; HSO delegate to Christian Council of Tanganyika; HSO continues translations to Swahili, 1950 May-Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Incl. re. HSO working on Turu grammar, catechism, and hymnal; death of fellow missionary Twilah Peterson; furlough - studying at Hartford Seminary and speaking in churches, 1951 Jan-Nov (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Incl. re. continuing studies at Hartford; son Howie Joe adopted; return to MN; deputation work in churches; return to Africa; 90 adults baptized, 1952 Jan - 1954 Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Incl. re. building church at Wilakina; HSO continues Turu translation; literacy program planned; HSO given 6 months for full time language research; motion passed that no African pastor or teacher can belong to a political party; literacy work in Kinampanda; furlough, 1955 Feb - 1957 Jul (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - HSO and LAO now teaching at Lutheran Theological College in Makumira; son Howie in MN attending school, 1970 Aug-1973 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters primarily to/from Howie in U.S., 1973 Jul-1974 Feb (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - HSO, and children Tim and Linda return to Tanzania; Louise and Sharon follow later; more letters to/from Howie, 1975 Feb-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - HSO Academic Dean at seminary in Makumira; more letters to/from Howie, 1976 Feb-Jun (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Augsburg Press to publish booklet of 20 African songs in English; HSO invited to teach at Pacific Lutheran Seminary in 1977, 1976 Jul - 1977 May (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Primarily letters to/from children, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
    - HSO and LAO on furlough for six months doing deputation work; HSO becomes editor of Africa Theological Journal, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters to children re. life at Makumira; HSO goes to conference in Uganda, 1983 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Incl. re. HSO advisor to ELCT Hymnal Committee; trip to U.S.; return to Makumira, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - Incl. re. publication of Africa Theological Journal; HSO translating Zulu hymns into Swahili; teaching students about African music; and re. children's activities, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Incl. HSO teaching re. African music and culture, publications; trip to Sweden for International Ecumencial Hymnological Research Conference, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - Incl. re. plans to retire from work in Tanzania; HSO offered interim job at Wartburg Seminary; and undated and fragmentary family correspondence, 1988, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Circular Letters
    - Circular letters describing work of the Olsons, 1947-1950, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General correspondence
    - Incl. letters to/from Desmond Cole, Dr. Henry A. Gleason, Jr, Herb Haferman, Dr. J. Maurice Honifel re. linguistics and HSO dissertation (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Incl. letters to/from Alpha Jaques, Marguerite Jellicoe, HSO to mission members, Jim Peters, Dean and Elaine Peterson, Bill Samarin, Carl Sandgren, Dr. Earl Stevick (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Writings, 1955-2004; Series II
  - Re. linguistics: Report of the Turu Translation Committee; progress reports on linguistic analysis; "An Introduction to Rimi Cosmogeny"; Rimi language study, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "African Traditional Music and Its Use in Worship", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Once in a Lifetime" - re. foot safari in the Ngorongoro Conservation Area; "Kibo Kwaheri" - re. climbing Mt. Kilimanjaro, 1985, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "A Descriptive Analysis of Rimi" - HSO Ph.D. dissertation, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - ELCA Writers Workshop at Concordia College, MN; HSO manuscripts from workshop, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - ELCA Writers Workshop at Concordia University, IL, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- African Music Documentation, Series III
  - African hymn books (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - "Tumshangilie Mungu" - African hymn manuscript (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Ethnic hymns (Box 3, Folder 37-40)
  - "Set Free" - original manuscript (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Conferences and Lay Courses, Series IV
  - Women's Retreat, Paisley, FL, 1994 Mar (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - East Africa Missionary Reunion: Concordia College, MN, 1994 Jul (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Sheridan Lutheran Church, Lincoln, NE: "Listening to Africa", 1995 Mar (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Community Church College: "Africa My Tutor", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - East Africa Missionary Reunion: Gustavus Adolphus College, MN, 1997 Jun (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Leadership Conference, Florida Synod, 1997 Sep (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Lutheran Lay School of Theology, Pinellas Park, FL: "Africa My Tutor", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
  - Lutheran Lay School of Theology curriculum information, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - East Africa Missionary Reunion: Bethany College, KS, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Esst Africa Missionary Reunion: Concordia College, MN, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Luther Hostel, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - "Singing Our Theology" - course outline, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 54)
- Collected Material, 1943-1991, n.d.; Series V
  - Reports, annual conference minutes re. work of Augustana Lutheran Mission work in Tanganyika (copies from ELCA archives), 1943-1954 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Report re. LCA World Missions; information about designated giving; report re. the history of the Africa Theological Journal, 1966-1991 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Christmas music (American) (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Booklet of Rimi proverbs; miscellaneous printed material (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Audio tapes (reel to reel) re. Rimi language (Box 4, Folder 59)
- Biographical Documentation, 2010, n.d.; Series VI
  - Biographical sketches, obituaries for HSO, genealogical information, 2010, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 60)